WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
Season four of Downton Abbey
left us with so many burning questions.
Will Lady Mary pick Tony Gillingham
or Charles Blake?
Let battle commence.
Did Mr. Bates kill Mr. Green,
and if so, will he be caught?
You know me, when I do a thing,
I like to have a very
good reason for doing it.
Will Edith be able
to see her daughter,
and whatever
happened to Gregson?
I want to know what's happened...
If he's trapped somewhere or
falsely imprisoned...
Or even dead.
Will Carson and Mrs. Hughes
finally walk down the aisle?
As a matter fact,
I know there is a wedding in season five,
but whose wedding?
Ooh, I couldn't ever answer that.
- So many questions.
- I need the answers.
Something to look forward to.
Please join me, Bernadette Peters,
for a loving look back
at the first four
seasons of Downton Abbey
and a tantalizing and exclusive
peek at season five
in Downton Abbey Rediscovered.
Sync by f1nc0
Corrected by icephoenix
www.MY-SUBS.com
Hi, I'm Bernadette Peters.
I'm a huge fan of Downton Abbey.
I just love the way they weave together
romance, intrigue, and drama,
so many great characters,
wonderful writing, and marvelous acting,
and so many urgent questions
that need answers.
Season five holds those answers,
but will there even be
a Downton Abbey?
Take a look at this season five clip.
Fire!
- What?
- Fire!
Oh, my God, George.
I got Sibby and George.
Thank God.
Mary, you take them.
Tony, go with her.
Tom, come with me.
You know where the sand buckets
are kept.
Good God!
Barrow, is she all right?!
I think so, M'Lord.
We must get her outside!
Quickly, Tom!
Oh, my goodness,
was that Edith's room,
and was Thomas
actually saving the day?
Looks like Downton Abbey
is off to a dramatic start,
and you know
we all love the drama.
Our program is called
Downton Abbey Rediscovered because
there have been so many twists
and turns after four seasons
that looking back at the plots,
characters, and spectacular locations
is a little like
rediscovering an old friend.
We just can't stop talking
about its most memorable moments.
Yes.
I won't allow it!
- Thank God.
- Yes. Thank God.
In these moments,
you can normally find
an Italian who isn't too picky.
So much has happened both
upstairs and downstairs during
the first four seasons of
Downton Abbey that I think a
bit made a reminder of our
favorite characters at the start
of the series might he helpful.
Downton Abbey is the ancestral
home of the Crawley family,
which always seems to be
on the verge of going under.
Robert, the current Earl of Grantham,
marries an American heiress, Cora,
to save Downton Abbey
and has three lovely daughters,
Lady Mary, Lady Edith, and Lady Sybil,
and no direct heir.
Downstairs,
we have tradition-bound butler Mr. Carson
and kind head housekeeper
Mrs. Hughes running the show.
Strict but caring cook Mrs. Patmore
and her kitchen maid Daisy.
We should go out to greet them.
- And me, Mr. Carson?
- No, Daisy, not you.
Ambitious and evil
Thomas the footman,
handsome Irish
chauffeur Branson,
Anna, ladies' maid
to the Crawley daughters,
and the mysterious Mr. Bates,
valet to Lord Grantham.
Of course, there's the dowager
Countess of Grantham, Violet,
played with so much breathtaking
aplomb by Dame Maggie Smith.
Her quips are quite something and
only getting better with each season.
- Good heavens. What am I sitting on?
- Uh, swivel chair.
Is this an instrument of
communication or torture?
What...
Hello?!
When you talk like that,
I'm tempted to ring for Nanny
and have you put to bed
with no supper.
That is all I have
to say on the subject.
One of the reasons
we love Downton Abbey
is the period and
culture in which it's set.
An aristocratic family,
the Crawleys, living large
in an enormous English country house
with a cadre of servants
to tend to their every need.
When William the Conqueror
defeated the Saxons in 1066,
he established a feudal system,
and ever since that date,
great families gained
huge amounts of land
and established power
and influence through it.
And so the Crawleys,
who emerged much, much later on
had, in their own way,
stepped into this tradition
of having huge influence
over a large amount of land,
and it was rather like
ruling a small country
because not only did they have
their own economy within that,
they were, in their own sense,
the rulers of the people who lived there.
You do not love the place yet.
- Well, obviously, it's...
- No, you don't love it.
You see a million bricks
that may crumble,
a thousand gutters and pipes
that may block and leak,
and stone that will crack
in the frost.
But you don't.
I see my life's work.
We picked the setting
of the first series originally
at the very height
of the British empire,
the very height
of the aristocratic system.
It never got any better than that
for those who were at the top,
and then of course the
First World War came and
smashed everything,
changed everything,
the world would
never be the same again.
Our story begins with
the sinking of the Titanic in 1912
which kills a Crawley cousin
and leaves Matthew Crawley,
a more distant cousin,
heir to the title.
- It's from Lord Grantham.
- Really?
What on earth does he want?
He wants to change our lives.
Matthew arrives at Downton
with his mother, Mrs. Crawley.
The Great War changes
the entire world
and shakes the very foundation
of Downton Abbey.
Women are training for work,
technology advances,
and the ancient social order
begins to crumble upstairs and down.
Youngest Crawley daughter Lady Sybil
scandalously falls for the
family's Irish chauffeur,
Tom Branson.
They elope, eventually return to Downton,
and have a baby.
And tragically, Sybil dies from
complications following childbirth.
Is there anything we should do,
Mr. Carson?
Carry on, Daisy,
as we all must.
After a lot of
"will they, won't they,"
future heir to Downton,
Matthew Crawley,
marries eldest daughter Lady Mary,
and they have a son, baby George.
Season three ends with Matthew's
unexpected and tragic death.
In season four, we watched Mary
transition from death to life
as she dealt with the loss of
her beloved husband Matthew.
We saw Edith take life by the horns
and have to deal with the consequences.
And we saw new romances start to
blossom from the most unexpected places.
But one of the most disturbing
moments in season four
was Anna's rape
by Lord Gillingham's valet, Mr. Green.
I still have nightmares about
that scene.
Now let me by please.
And Bates' response?
Did he kill Mr. Green?
He has quite the temper.
We'll find out in season five.
Perhaps the most asked question
is will Lady Mary find love again
after losing the love of her life?
And will it be Charles Blake or
Tony Gillingham?
Or perhaps even someone else?
Season five starts nine months on
from where we left it in the last episode,
and it becomes quite clear
that one of those two
has certainly been
seeing quite a lot of Mary
in that time.
There was a time when you were
torn between me and Charles Blake,
but I think you've decided
and I'm the winner.
Well,
thank goodness that's settled.
But of course the thing about
Mary is she wants it all,
and she's used to having it all,
so things are never quite
plain sailing.
It never is simple with Mary.
She has a hard time deciding
what her heart really desires.
Take a look at this season five clip.
Is Charles Blake trying
to help Lady Mary,
or is he just setting up his
advantage for her hand?
Nothing will make me happier
than seeing you happy,
but please be absolutely sure
before you decide.
- Why do you say that?
- Because you're cleverer than he is.
That might've worked
in the last century
when ladies had to hide their brains
behind good manners
and good breeding but not now.
I don't agree.
I think Tony is quite as clever as I am.
Then one of us is right.
And one is wrong.
The thing is with Mary
is that she...
She makes these impulsive decisions,
and then, you know,
she'll follow through with it,
and then afterwards discovers
that it probably wasn't a very good idea.
I can't wait to find out what happens
with Lady Mary and her eligible bachelors,
but what about Lady Edith?
Unfortunately,
her life pales in comparison to Mary's.
Her situation leaves
much to be desired.
That might be the understatement
of the year.
After being jilted at the altar,
Lady Edith falls in love
with a married editor, Michael Gregson,
and just when things
seem to be working in her favor,
she gets pregnant,
and her suitor goes missing.
I was happy that Edith
chose to have the child,
a scandal still under wraps,
but I doubt for long.
Poor Edith.
She struck up a deal
with Mr. Drew
that he will take care of
this child for her.
She's obviously going to be
visiting the farmer's house a lot,
and obviously, she has to find a way
of doing that without raising suspicion.
And the more
she sees her own daughter,
of course, the more she wants to see,
and that starts to give us problems.
We've almost forgotten she's
not one of our own, haven't we, Tim?
She's just lovely.
- How pretty your hair is, darling.
- We sometimes wonder where she
got her coloring,
but I never knew her parents.
- No?
- No.
I think that in series five,
Edith is less inclined
to be told no and to be made unhappy
by other people's choices.
She takes a leaf out of Mary's book...
Although she would kill me
for saying so...
And she actually
starts to control her own life.
- It's very dangerous.
- It's a very risky situation.
If someone guesses or
if she's showing too much attention,
then it could all...
All go wrong.
So the potential for scandal is still
very much hanging over Lady Edith.
Here's a look at a scene from
season five.
It looks like her secret might
not be as hidden as she hoped.
The real reason's a good
reason to love a child, m'lady.
Mothers should love their children.
- How long have you known?
- Since you asked me to take her in.
But you're quite safe.
It's not my place to judge you,
and I wouldn't anyway.
But I should control my feelings.
I could say yes,
but I don't believe it's realistic.
I don't believe you could.
Then what are you saying?
We need a way for you to live the truth
without telling the truth.
I'm not sure secret like that
can be hidden for long.
Will the family find out?
And what will it mean for Edith
and her reputation?
Oh, the scandal, the intrigue,
it is intoxicating, isn't it?
And there's a so much more to
look forward to in season five.
I can't wait.
You've got late-flowering love.
You have the choices in
relationships.
You have relationships being
tested by society at large.
You have scandal.
And you have a marriage that
survives rough waters.
There is a theme in the fifth season
of things from one's past
and nothing being
quite as you expect it to be.
So we have this, in my opinion,
absolutely delicious storyline
where Violet had a bit of a shady past
that has been buried for a very long time.
I mean, one way or another,
everyone goes down the aisle
with half the story hidden.
We've got
Sophie's character Daisy who's,
you know, wanting to educate herself,
which I think is great,
and she's starting to sort of
get her voice.
"Arithmetic part one, cost accounting"?
What is this?
I was rubbish at numbers at school.
Well, all the best people were
rubbish at numbers at school.
But I don't know anything.
You talk about my working
at Mr. Mason's farm, but how?
I couldn't balance the books
if my life depended on it.
Why do you need to?
Because I want to be grown-up,
Mrs. Patmore.
I want responsibility.
I want to be an adult.
I can't just stand here following
orders for the rest of my life.
What education and knowledge
does for all these people
is to give them choices.
And choices weren't something
that people had before.
And that I think is what's the sort of
running theme through series five.
There are suddenly
more choices for people.
And series five definitely
has even greater revelations
for people in relation to the
possibilities outside of Downton
and within Downton as well.
Thomas comes to mind as
one of the biggest ones.
He really takes his own life in
hand and tries to... tries to
make changes in his own life,
and I think it's one of the most
compelling stories we have this year.
It's a fantastic story
because you sort of
scratch the surface
of Thomas more,
and you realize that he's a person
that just wants to find love
and find somebody
that accepts him for who he is.
If anyone had told me that
I'd have been friends with a...
A man like you,
I'd have not have believed them.
But we have been friends.
I hope you find some happiness.
I do, truly.
I think that what we're
finding in season five is the world
is changing and people are...
The younger generation,
certainly, is saying,
"no, we're not going to marry
someone who's just suitable."
And that's the running story
through the romance
and the intrigue
and the scandal in this is...
It's young people saying,
"I'll marry for love
and not because he's got all the right...
He ticks all the right boxes for family."
The war
and the changes that followed
have created a younger,
freer generation.
People want to be happy
and live the life they want,
not necessarily the one that has
been laid out for them.
Even Lady Mary and Lord Gillingham
are taking hold of these new ideas.
Here's a season five clip
that's quite saucy.
I wonder what Mary will say.
I want you to come away,
just for a week, maybe less,
but on our own.
And I want to spend the days
talking.
- And the nights?
- We'll spend those together, too.
I want us to be lovers, Mary.
What do you say to
my scandalous suggestion?
Oh, my,
what will Lady Mary say?
If she agrees,
this has scandal written all over it.
I love it.
There are so many unanswered questions
in season five still left to discuss.
One I am dying to find
out is if Mr. Bates
really did push Mr. Green
in front of that car.
I never was 100% convinced that he was
innocent in the death of his wife, Vera.
When we come back,
we'll look at the men of Downton Abbey,
Carson, Robert, Branson, and Bates,
and the women they love,
plus some more tantalizing
moments from season five.
You just won't want to miss it,
so stay tuned.
In the first part of our program,
we brought you up to date
with all the twists and turns
at Downton Abbey
during the first four seasons
and let you in on some really
exciting scenes from season five.
Now we'll look at the men of Downton
and the women they love, of course.
This is Downton Abbey, after all.
Whether fighting in the war,
romancing beautiful women,
or battling to save the estate,
the men of Downton upstairs and down
are pivotal to the riveting plot
lines of Downton Abbey.
Think of young Matthew coming
to save the day in season one
or Branson's transformation
from chauffeur to estate manager
or Thomas's evil,
devious nature
changing over four seasons into well,
his evil, devious nature.
Hmm, this guy hasn't changed
much at all, has he?
Or Mosley's amusing yet
misfortunate life struggles.
Will he find love with Baxter?
Where will that go in season five?
I wonder if...
And then there's Bates.
Perhaps the most burning
question of season four was
did Bates kill Mr. Green
to avenge his wife,
and will that come back
to haunt both he and Anna?
Such drama.
But let's start with Robert,
Earl of Grantham.
No one is more central to
Downton Abbey.
Robert is a man who has been
born into a somewhat tricky position
in that his destiny is mapped out
from the day of his birth,
which is to take over and manage
and hand on the estate of Downton Abbey.
So he never goes out
into the real world, so to speak.
He's served in the army.
He's fought in the World War,
but he's never really experienced life
beyond the estate.
So his destiny really is to
manage Downton to the best of his ability.
My fortune is the work of others
who labored to build a great dynasty.
Do I have the right
to destroy their work
or impoverish that dynasty?
I am a custodian, my dear,
not an owner.
I must strive to be worthy of
the task I've been set.
I always say
sort of woe betide him
if Downton goes under
on his watch.
You know,
the shame would be immense.
Downton Abbey,
if it were a real place,
would probably not exist
by the end of the 20th century,
or if it did continue to exist,
it would be a shadow of its former self.
Robert is not cut out to be wise enough
to navigate his way
through those waters.
He's not cut out
for the world of business.
So his very role is attacked
from every possible quarter.
So people really could lose
vast fortunes in speculation
and because of scams
and all manner of different things.
It wasn't just me.
Everyone said we couldn't lose.
We knew hard times were coming
for estates like Downton,
and this investment would make it
safe for the rest of time.
The fact is, the company is
about to be declared bankrupt.
Are you really telling me
that all the money is gone?
I'm afraid so.
The lion's share of Cora's fortune?
You can't have
a good drama without jeopardy,
and Robert seems to find pretty good ways
of jeopardizing the whole situation.
It must be in the Crawley blood,
because Robert's father
also left Downton in dire
financial circumstances,
so much so that years earlier,
Robert was forced to find
an American heiress to save the day,
Cora Levinson.
She has saved his bacon,
and that's why when he loses her money,
this is just the
worst possible nightmare
because he should
never have had the money anyway,
you know, he took her
almost in a fast-handed way.
And that creates a kind of bond
that I think is very,
very strong between them.
And what we try to show,
they are different.
Cora, again, is much more modern.
I mean,
when Downton is threatened
and they may lose it all
and everything,
she's sorry,
but she's mainly sorry for him.
How terrible for you.
It's not so good for you.
Don't worry about me.
I'm an American.
Have gun, will travel.
Oh, thank God for you anyway.
The changes that the new century
bring are far more in tune
with her original American philosophies
than Robert's old-school British stuff.
So actually,
as the show has gone on,
Cora is much more forthright in her beliefs
of where she thinks they're wrong
and the new way is right.
I think what happens by season five
is the men really start to realize
what their true place is,
and I think Robert increasingly realizes
that he has to have a more equal
partnership with Cora.
She's very good for Robert
because she is the one that
eases him into a changing world
after the First World War
and helps him to psychologically adapt.
Robert?
A world-famous singer
is in our house,
a great artist honored by the king,
but you felt it beneath your dignity
to eat with her?
- I don't...
Am I the only member of this family
who lives in the 20th century?
- What room is she in?
- Princess Amelia, my Lady.
You will have her next to you at dinner,
and you will like it.
But what do I say to her?
What does one say to a singer?
There's never a moment
when he says,
"is it right that I should be an earl
and I should own 20,000 acres
"and I should be living this life,
and not through my own efforts at all,
just because I was born in the
right bed at the right time?"
So I feel that that, in a sense,
is where Robert can be caught out
is when people
challenge that position.
Poor Robert.
The new world is challenging him
in so many ways,
and he has trouble
moving with the tide.
It looks like in season five,
his ego takes a few more hits.
Take a look at this clip.
But is that why you're here,
to ask for a piece of land as
the site for this thing?
That's why were here to see you,
m'lord,
but we'd also like to offer the position
of chairman of our committee to...
I'll take over now.
You were saying?
We'd like Mr. Carson to be
chairman of our committee.
But... Surely his Lordship...
No, Carson, they don't want me,
they want you.
Yikes, I'm not sure who that
was more shocking for,
Robert or Carson.
This world certainly is moving
in a new direction
when a butler is chosen
to lead over a lord.
In a way, this new world is even
harder for Carson to wrap his
head around.
He is the true keeper of
traditions and lives and dies
by the social rules that
have been the foundation
of these families and
houses for generations.
Carson is definitely much
more wedded to the structure
and the necessary order of this
little society than Robert is.
Carson really is reluctant to change
in any way, shape or form,
but he's the bedrock
on which Robert relies,
and he's the absolute pillar
of the establishment.
He's like the 10 commandments in a person,
do you know what I mean?
He's like that sort of...
we know "Thou shalt nots,"
all the "thou shalt nots,"
and they're all embodied by him.
It's like he's the house in person.
You must remember that
a good servant at all times
retains a sense of pride and dignity
that reflects the pride and dignity
of the family he serves.
And never make me
remind you of it again.
Carson is really the most
establishment man in the house,
including the family.
He believes in the system more than anyone,
more than Robert does.
- You mustn't take it personally.
- I do take it personally, Mrs. Hughes.
Can't stand by and watch our family
threatened with the loss
of all they hold dear.
- They're not our family.
- Well, they're all the family I've got.
Mrs. Hughes is a
wise and kind woman
but who is unfettered
by the class imprisonment.
She is not a revolutionary.
She's not abusive or rude to them.
She quite likes them, really,
but she doesn't worship them,
and she doesn't worship the system,
and so there is a real contrast,
and together, Jim and Phyllis
have created this duo.
I describe it as a marriage.
It's a nonsexual marriage,
but it is a sort of marriage nonetheless.
There is a real warmth and
mutual understanding.
I mean, she thinks
he's a bit of an old fuddy-duddy
and could loosen his braces a bit,
you know,
but they feel very warm
towards each other,
but they also respect one another's work
ethic and everything like that,
and so in many ways,
they would be a perfect match.
Everybody wants Carson
and Mrs. Hughes quietly to get together.
- I knew I hadn't thrown it away.
- Who is she?
Just a friend at one time.
What was she called?
Alice. Alice Neil.
And you were fond of her.
I was, but people drift in
and out of your life, don't they?
You see, we get glimpses
of Carson all the way through.
We know that
underneath that exterior
beats a very,
very romantic heart.
And the very end of season four
was a delicious moment
where she finally thinks,
oh, enough of this,
come along, hold my hand.
Suppose I fall over.
Suppose a bomb goes off.
Suppose we're hit by a falling star.
You can hold my hand.
Then we'll both go in together.
I think I will hold your hand.
It'll make me feel a bit steadier.
You can always hold my hand
if you need to feel steady.
I don't know how,
but you manage to make that sound
a little risque.
And if I did?
We're getting on, Mr. Carson,
you and I.
We can afford to live a little.
Really, we,
we the creators and we the audience,
have to see if they do
make that final furlong.
And that's all you're gonna get.
I would love to see Carson
and Mrs. Hughes get together,
and it was so wonderful to watch them
walk into the ocean hand in hand.
I have a feeling that we will
see more of that in season five.
There are so many
interesting men at Downton...
Thomas the footman with his deep secret,
Matthew Crawley, who we lost so
tragically at the end of season three,
the missing Michael Gregson,
Edith's paramour and father of her love child,
and Tom Branson,
the handsome Irish chauffeur,
who woos the youngest daughter
of the Crawley family, Lady Sybil.
Tom has been on such a
journey throughout.
From series one to where we find him
now at the end of four,
and he has had to make
a few sacrifices
in relation to his political beliefs
and then with his wife passing.
He's had to make huge sacrifices
in relation to how we deals
with the family.
He's constantly on a knife edge
because he's not really
part of either world anymore,
and he is trying to fit in to
this lifestyle which is not his
and never really what he wanted.
He's sort of trapped
in this bizarre world.
And these are your people now.
You must remember that.
This is your family.
This may be my family,
but these are not quite my people.
That sounds like a challenge.
Partly his plot in the fifth series
is that suddenly he starts to
remember who he really is
and not to pull back from them
in an emotional way
but to kind of remember
that he doesn't agree with
a lot of this stuff that he's been nodding at,
you know, as he ate his soup.
- Don't call her "Your Grace."
- I thought it was correct.
For a servant
or an official at a ceremony,
but in a social situation,
- call her Duchess.
- But why?
- I don't call you Countess.
- Certainly not.
- There's no logic in it.
- Oh, no, if I were to search for logic,
I should not look for it
among the English upper class.
I think it'll be interesting
to see in five where Tom ends up
because I think we're getting to
the point that Tom's either
going to have to bed in and
really become part of this family
and just embrace it or I think he's going to
have to maybe set off for distant shores.
As marvelous Irish actor
Allen Leech just said,
Branson's future may involve travel.
Wait a second, did he just reveal the plot
from the upcoming season?
What about little Sibby?
I can't imagine that'll go over
well with the family.
- Uh-oh.
- Uh-oh!
In all of Downton Abbey,
one of the most fascinating,
enigmatic, and complex characters is
John Bates, valet to Robert Crawley.
A cloudy past,
accusations of wrongdoing,
and yet we really like him,
don't we?
Maybe it's his pure and true
love of Anna.
Bates is the man with the past.
He's a man who has suffered,
but he's got a quality of being able
to be very opaque and yet sympathetic.
You don't know what's going on,
and yet you're on his side.
I still think it's funny given
that he's a convicted murderer.
May I remind you, Mr. Barrow,
that in this house,
Mr. Bates is a wronged man
seeking justice.
If you have any problems with that definition,
I suggest you eat in the yard.
All the way through,
you have these situations,
and you're not quite sure.
You know, I mean, even with Vera,
we're not 100% sure he didn't do it,
and yet we're really pleased
he got off, you know.
There's a wonderful little
moment in the prison where he
just throws someone against the
wall, and you see what the
potential of this man can be.
You can see what a fighter he
could be.
Don't ever threaten me.
I forgot I was sharing a cell
with a murderer.
Don't forget it again.
And yet 90% of the time,
you're seeing a man of great
gentleness and humility and dignity.
So the mystery is there.
Bates' better half is Anna.
I just love Anna,
ladies' maid to Lady Mary.
She is kind, steadfast,
and unwavering in her love of Mr. Bates.
She is one of those people
who has found someone
who they can love 100%,
and he has found someone whom
he can love 100%.
But where it becomes slightly frightening
in the case of someone like Bates
is that when you have someone
who is potentially violent
and explosive and a bomb,
of course in one way,
it's lovely that they love you,
but in another way,
you're living with an unexploded bomb,
and Anna has
this almost frightening awareness
that when she is assaulted,
part of her struggle has to be
to conceal it from her husband.
- We must tell someone.
- No, no, no.
- But you have to tell Mr. Bates.
- Him least of all.
If you knew, he'd murder the man
who's done it, and then he'll be hanged.
- But surely...
- He's a convicted felon.
Do you think they'd
spare him second time?
No.
Maybe the doctor's still here.
Will you listen?
I need your help
or I wouldn't have told you.
Nobody else must ever know.
You promise me?
Assaulted and afraid of
what her husband might do,
many tears were shed for poor Anna
in season four.
Did Bates avenge her rape by
killing the despicable Mr. Green?
Did Lady Mary help cover up a crime
by burning his ticket to London?
Here's a season five clip that
might just provide some answers.
Ah, how can I help you?
Well, it's an odd business,
but we may as well get down to it.
A man stayed here last year,
a Mr. Alex Green, worked for Lord Gillingham.
I remember him well.
Why wouldn't I when he died so
very tragically not long after?
Well, that's all I need.
I've just been told to check
that you remember him and...
Oh, thank you.
And to give warning that we
might need to ask some questions.
I don't understand.
Well, something's turned up,
and before they take it further,
they're trying to establish its significance.
But what is that?
What's turned up?
A witness.
Yikes, tell me it's not so.
Give this poor couple a few moments of
happiness, will you please?
Anna and Bates have endured far
more than their share of tragedy.
When we come back,
we'll look at
love, lies, and scandal at Downton Abbey...
So yummy...
And have some more exclusive scenes
from the upcoming season,
some
real hum-dingers.
Don't miss it.
In the second part of our program,
we looked at the men of Downton
and the women they love...
Robert and Cora, Bates and Anna,
and Carson and Mrs. Hughes.
I do so hope that that one works out.
And we let you in on some
marvelous moments from season five.
Now the juicy part.
Without love, lives, and scandal,
I'm not sure there would
even be a Downton Abbey.
One of the hallmarks
of a great family...
Certainly in Britain,
and this is true today...
Is the one thing they
hate is scandal.
You will figure in a
scandal of such magnitude,
it will never be forgotten until
long after we're both dead.
I'll be ruined, Mama.
On the whole, the upper classes
want to figure in the papers three times...
When they're born,
when they marry, and when they die...
But that is a form of blackmail
that is very potent.
Such as Lady Mary's
predicament with ruthless
newspaper proprietor and former
fiance Richard Carlisle.
If you think you can jilt me
or in some way set me aside,
I tell you now you have given me
the power to destroy you,
and don't think I won't use it.
Downton's very much about
secrets and who knows what
and who knows more than the other,
and I think people like having
knowledge of other people's lives.
It really is
the heart of the show.
You see, if you don't come back to me,
I'm going to the newspapers
with a cracking story.
And I'd like to bet the
Granthams won't survive it.
The public's bored with the war,
you see.
They like gossip,
and a diplomat dying in the bed of
an earl's unmarried daughter,
well, that takes the ticket for
the tale of the year.
Our historical advisor,
Alastair Bruce,
sort of said to me one day on the set,
he said,
"All of this,"
and he was pointing to the castle,
he said, "all of this relies
on the fact that you behave
"in a certain way, that you are
the upstanding members of this community
"and that people look
to you as the lords and ladies,
as sort of the pillars of the
community."
And the more you have to
present this front
of a fully functioning family
where everyone is perfectly marvelous
and so on, I mean,
there never was
and never will be
a fully functioning family.
That will never happen
in any civilization on Earth.
When something bad happens,
there's no point in wishing it
had not happened.
The only option is
to minimize the damage.
Violet, the Dowager Countess
of Grantham is so very practical.
She knows that the Crawleys
have had their share...
Maybe even more than their share...
Of scandal.
We've already looked at
the social disgrace
of Lady Sybil
marrying the Irish chauffeur
and of Robert's nearly calamitous
loss of Cora's fortune.
Here's a memorable scandal
from season one
that nearly brought down
the walls of Downton Abbey.
Mr. Pamuk,
the handsome Turkish attache,
finds eldest Crawley daughter
Lady Mary irresistible.
I have to say, I think probably
Mr. Pamuk is my favorite
of all those stories,
purely because I think it is
the epitome of Julian's skillful writing
that, you know,
he was only in a tiny amount,
he was in a few scenes,
but everybody remembers him,
and I'm sure Theo, who played him,
is very grateful for that.
He doesn't look Turkish at all.
Well, he doesn't look like
any Englishman I've ever met,
worse luck.
I think he's beautiful.
I mean, it was such a great storyline,
and of course, based on true fact.
Mr. Pamuk!
- What happened?
- I don't know.
Heart attack, I suppose,
or a stroke or...
He was alive, and suddenly he cried out,
and then he was dead.
We must cover him up.
Mama!
Edith finds out,
and when Mary scorns her one too many times,
she decides to write to
the Turkish embassy and tell
them what happened
to their diplomat.
Before mass communication,
the letter was this incredibly
powerful agent of scandal.
The love letters, the trysts,
the arrangements,
the notes that were left
beneath pillows
and slipped into handbags
and tucked into gloves,
all of them, you know,
quite capable of blowing
a marriage out of the water.
And that was a sort of
ripple of danger
they all lived with
and of course indulged.
You know, there is something
about human beings that they
like to take risks, and I think we,
you know, in Downton,
we just sort of plug into that.
You know, my mother's always
telling me never put anything in writing.
And now thanks to you,
I never will again.
The first four seasons of
Downton Abbey takes place
between 1912 and 1923,
and writer Julian Fellowes
and the whole production team
have taken great pains
to get every period detail correct,
including some
cultural biases that today
may seem politically incorrect
or even abhorrent,
such as the scandal of homosexuality.
Remember this scene when Thomas,
the man with a secret,
misunderstands his fellow
servant Jimmy's kindness?
What are you doing?!
Why are you in here?!
Because of all there is between us.
There's nothing between us
except my fist if you don't get out!
We see some quite realistic
and horrible attitudes towards Thomas,
you know?
Homophobic attitudes,
because that's what it was like then.
To finally discuss that and see that
and see Thomas completely destroyed
and just at the end of it
a vulnerable human being
who just needs affection
and has never been given it.
I cannot hide that I find
your situation revolting,
but whether or not you believe me,
I am not entirely unsympathetic.
You have been twisted
by nature into something foul,
and even I can see
that you did not ask for it.
I'm not foul, Mr. Carson.
I'm not the same as you,
but I am not foul.
Carson would dearly love to
get rid of Thomas,
but when getting rid of Thomas
means that there will be a family scandal
and the scandal would reflect
badly on the house,
then the pragmatic side of Carson
comes out, and he thinks,
right, well I'll suppress my personal
feelings for this loathsome person
and for the good of the house,
I will swallow my pride and accept him.
Carson's reluctant acceptance
of Thomas's homosexuality
mirrors the feelings of society
at large in this period.
Perhaps this has twisted Thomas
into the nefarious character
we love to hate.
Here, Thomas blackmails Baxter,
Lady Cora's maid,
to spy on members
of the Crawley family.
What deep secret does he hold
over her?
You've got to find out more.
- But how?
- You'll think of something.
Thomas and Baxter have history.
He has a dark secret
that he knows about her,
so he has a hold over her.
Basically, the situation that
she has found herself in
is one that would mean she would not
be able to work in those times.
She would probably have to
live in a poor house
and maybe work as a prostitute
if she wanted to get any food, really.
So Thomas gets somebody
who's very down on their luck
and goes, "I can help,
but you'll have to help me back."
So that's the carrot that he dangles,
and then the stick is very much,
"you don't get something for nothing, love.
"You're gonna be my eyes and ears
on the ground upstairs,
and you're going to tell me everything
that goes on, and I can use this."
So he's very much got himself
an upstairs spy.
Now listen...
What you have to decide is
where your first loyalties are.
With her... Or with me?
All right.
- Have it your own way.
- Oh, I intend to.
Baxter does find a friend in Moseley,
formerly valet to Matthew Crawley
and currently a footman at Downton
and one of my favorite characters.
I think they have a shared
kinship between them.
Certainly, they have both seen
their share of misfortune.
I think he feels with Baxter
that there have been injustices
in her life, and...
And so I think he responds to that.
And he knows that
Thomas has a history of
manipulating circumstance
and manipulating people.
And so he feels that Baxter is
at the rough end of that
and wants to put a sort of
a comforting arm around her.
Leave her alone, Mr. Barrow.
We don't want any bullying
brought back from overseas,
do we, Ms. Baxter?
Now are there any stalls
you'd still like to see?
Thomas doesn't take kindly to
Moseley's interference in season five,
and his patience grows thin
with Baxter withholding valuable information
which he could use to spread his misery
and better his position in the house.
Will Thomas reveal Baxter's
dark secret?
Will that crush the budding
affections of Baxter and Mosley
and send her away from Downton?
Take a look at this season five clip.
There's no point trying to
find Mr. Mosley...
Because he can't help you now.
If that's how you want to play it,
I'll give you until
upstairs dinner has finished.
After which,
I will ask to speak to her Ladyship,
and I will tell her your story.
Do you hear what I'm saying?
- I can't tell you what I don't know.
- But you know something.
And I think it links Mr. Bates
to the dead valet.
Um, I just don't
like that Thomas Barrow.
Season five will reveal Baxter's secret,
and it's a doozy.
I just can't wait.
In season four,
we met many new characters,
and one in particular was scandalous
just to lay eyes on.
Is anyone there?
I think this is where we're
supposed to be.
When he actually arrives at Downton,
this is a complete shock.
The below stairs staff have perhaps
almost never seen a black man.
I particularly enjoyed
the scene below stairs
when he arrives and Carson,
as soon as he claps eyes on Jack,
you know,
he's completely shocked.
Welcome to Downton.
And this then follows, of course,
this extremely awkward conversation.
Have you never thought of
visiting Africa?
And why should I go to Africa,
Mr. Carson?
I'm no more African than you are.
It's really interesting to
see all the different
characters' attitudes towards race,
and certainly,
some of the characters are more
forward-thinking and open-minded than others.
Certainly, Cousin Rose
is a character who is always
forward-thinking,
perhaps more so than any other.
To Rose, Jack Ross was not only
a talented singer
but an enticing eligible bachelor.
Remember, this was the 1920s.
Interracial relationships were
a rare thing,
but cousin Rose is always
breaking down barriers, isn't she,
and seizing the moment?
Don't... Don't do that.
Rose is immature, and she's rash.
She follows her heart.
She doesn't think too carefully
about things,
and I think that any suggestion of
a relationship there
is completely out of the question
and would be disastrous for Rose.
Rose, I like you very much.
I want you to know.
But?
Well, what can we hope
to come out of all this?
Can't we just be in the moment?
I don't know many men like you,
and you don't know
many girls like me.
- Ain't that the truth?
- Then let's enjoy it.
You know what the French say...
vive la difference
I didn't want Jack to turn
into someone we feel sorry for.
I mean,
he's a very successful man.
He's a successful singer.
He's got a good career,
but nevertheless,
society at that time
was comparatively racist
in that even people
who were perfectly normal
would still have difficulty
accepting that union.
And certainly,
the color issue is a non-starter.
Jack knows that, really,
and it doesn't take terribly much to persuade him.
Tell me honestly,
do you think you can survive
what they'll do to you?
Because
I don't believe Rose could.
It may come as something of
a relief for you to hear that
I will not be marrying Rose.
You won't?
No.
I don't want to spoil her life.
Alas, Rose and Jack
were not meant to be.
What will season five hold
for our rebellious Rose?
Are there new taboo dalliances
coming up?
I'll be keeping an eye on her.
Certainly Rose is not the only
one to indulge in some
scandalous love affairs.
My dear, this is...
Isn't what it seems.
Is there room for misinterpretation?
Remember when Robert
was caught kissing a maid
or Lady Edith kissing the farmer
and later falling in love with
a married man
and having his love child?
I suspect there will be much
more about this in season five.
Since Matthew's unexpected death
at the end of season three,
we've all been wondering if
Lady Mary will ever love again.
Well, season four certainly gave
us two suitable candidates,
Charles Blake and Tony Gillingham.
By the end of the season,
Mary seems torn between the two.
But as we saw
earlier in our program,
Lord Gillingham proposed that
he and Mary get to know each other
while away for a weekend
to see how they get on.
Let's see what Lady Mary decided.
It's mad not to give
a false name.
Always make a lie
as truthful as possible.
How did you manage to
get the rooms connected?
Well, I'm not a complete half-wit.
Nor, happily, is the manager.
So, what's the plan?
It's a simple one.
We'll go down to Church Street
for a scrumptious dinner,
after which...
We'll come back.
- And make love.
- Exactly.
We'll make love all night,
and in fact,
for as long as either of us
has any stamina left.
And who can say fairer than that?
Oh, my, my, does this mean that
Mary will marry Tony, Lord Gillingham?
What will happen
if the family finds out?
I know there is a wedding
in season five, but is it Mary's?
That's why Julian Fellowes
always keeps us guessing.
Stay with us after
this brief intermission,
and we'll have another scene
from season five
that might give us a clue to
who's getting married in our upcoming season.
You won't want to miss it.
Thank you for joining me,
Bernadette Peters,
for this loving look back
at all things Downton Abbey.
It's been so much fun.
As we've mentioned,
here's an exclusive look at
a few more moments from season five.
- Isn't it absurd?
- I don't know,
might be rather fun for her to reinvent herself
as a great lady of the county.
For the last time, are you certain
you know what you're doing?
I believe so.
Fashionably late is one thing.
I'm fairly sure this was our
very biggest day in the history
of Downton Abbey in the sense
that literally everybody in the town,
everybody upstairs,
everybody downstairs is all
gathered for this big moment.
Need your help. If you see anyone
that shouldn't be filming,
if you see anyone with a phone,
with a camera they shouldn't have,
please report it
to an A.D. straightaway.
We want to keep this special for
the British public,
and that means not having a photo
of our bride on the front page
of a paper tomorrow.
Sync by f1nc0
Corrected by icephoenix
www.MY-SUBS.com